Guide to the Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Records WAG.054
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Records
1911-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island
WAG.054
27 Linear Feet in 26 record cartons and 1 flat box.
In 1911, the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor chartered the Central Union Label Council of New York City. Like its parent body, which had been established by Samuel Gompers in 1909, the New York City Label Council was dedicated to "a more systematic and thorough agitation and demand for union-made and particularly union label products, and for the patronage of union organizations issuing them." The Label Council, and later its state counterpart, focused on lobbying, service and publicity, all in the interest of union-labeled goods produced by members of craft unions. The records of the Central Union Label Council and its related organizations consist of correspondence, reports, flyers, news releases, programs, convention proceedings, speeches and publications, as well as non-print material such as photographs, buttons and posters. The collection documents both the behind­ the-scenes operation of this union public relations program as well as the implementation of that program, documented in its many publications and reports.
Arrangement
The records of Union Label are divided into twelve series:
Series I: Union Label Advocate
Series II: Union Label Store
Series III: Central Union Label Council
Series IV: Officers Correspondence
Subseries A: General Subseries B: Officers Activities Series V: Union Label and Service Trades Department - AFL and AFL-CIO
Series VI: Financial Records
Series VII: NYS Union Label and Serve Trades Department (ULSTD) Conventions
Series VIII: Public Relations and Organization Files
Series IX: Union Label Activities
Series X: Subject Files
Series XI: Publications
Series XII is comprised of materials from an accretion.
Historical Note
In 1911, the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor chartered the Central Union Label Council of New York City. Like its parent body, which had been established by Samuel Gompers in 1909, the New York City Label Council was dedicated to "a more systematic and thorough agitation and demand for union-made and particularly union label products, and for the patronage of union organizations issuing them." In 1916, the Council sold stock to establish a department store of union label products, which it then ran and stocked. After World War II, the increasing number of retail stores carrying union-made products greatly increased, prompting the Council to close its store in 1947.
The Label Council, and later its state counterpart, focused on lobbying, service and publicity, all in the interest of union-labeled goods produced by members of craft unions. Although separate central bodies existed in Manhattan and Brooklyn in 1911, the Central Union Label Council, headquartered in Brooklyn in its own building at 902-4 Broadway, bridged the boroughs. Charles Sinnigen, a member of the Electrotypers Local 100, served as the Council's Secretary. In 1935, the Union Label Trades and Services Department of the AFL chartered a Union Label Trades and Services Department for the state of New York. The organization moved to Bible House, where Charles Sinnigen directed both the city and the state organization as Secretary-Treasurer. The state organization called conventions annually and published the Union Label News.
After Sinnigen's death in 1949, Harry Avrutin, formerly an organizer for the Office and Professional Employees International Union, was elected Secretary-Treasurer of the Union Label and Services Trades Council of Greater New York. Placing greater emphasis on publicity tactics, Avrutin published annual buyers' guides to union-made products, mounted labor-management trade shows during "Union Label Week" (the first week of September), staged a "Miss Union Maid" beauty contest, sponsored a weekly Labor Press radio program, and engaged in other public relations efforts designed to promote union labor and products, and, increasingly, to encourage unionized business to remain in the metropolitan area. In 1959, the New York Council expanded its jurisdiction to Nassau and Suffolk Counties.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island, 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.032.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
A portion of the collection was microfilmed as part of the New York Labor documentation Project in 1985. The microfilm call number associated with this collection is R-7417. Included are a complete run of minutes for the Central Union Label Council (1911-1962) and Union Label Store, Inc. (1916-1945), The Union Label Advocate (1918-1932), and reports of Charles Sinnigen (1939-1946).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Photographs (PHOTOS 013)
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Lantern Slides (PHOTOS 024)
Scope and Contents
The records of the Central Union Label Council and its related organizations consist of correspondence, reports, flyers, news releases, programs, convention proceedings, speeches and publications, as well as non-print material such as photographs, buttons and posters. The collection documents both the behind­ the-scenes operation of this union public relations program, largely through the officers correspondence and the Executive Committee Minutes of the Central Union Label Council, as well as the implementation of that program, documented in its many publications and reports. Gaps are most evident in regards to the records of the ULSTD of NYS where early annual convention material is much less bulky than during the later years when H. Avrutin was Secretary-Treasurer. Meeting minutes for the Executive Council of that organization are also spotty.
Correspondence between the ULSTD of the AFL in Washington, D.C. and the New York branch is a significant part of the Officers' Correspondence file. C. Sinnigen stayed in close touch with I.M. Ornburn, Secretary-Treasurer of the national organization, and followed policy from that office. Materials from Series V on the ULSTD of the AFL show the extent to which the New York organizations followed the publicity programs of the Washington office. On the other hand, the New York office functioned as a national center for information about where to purchase union made goods and about which companies were organized. The Washington office used the Official Directory of AFL-CIO Union Products and Services (published by the ULSTD-NYS) as a national guide.
The work of Union Label as a lobbying organization is represented by letter writing campaigns to the New York City and New York state political leadership and by the inclusion of political leaders in Union Label publicity programs. Extensive involvement in labor-sponsored community programs by the leadership is also documented.
This collection is significant for its documentation at the city and state levels of larger national trends for American labor - the strengths and weaknesses of craft unionism in the 1930's and 1940's, the revitalization which came about from a merger with the industrial union movement, the expulsion of the Left from the labor movement in the 1950's and the existence of a more hostile environment for unions in the 1970's and 80's.
Major subject areas likewise shift from disputes about CIO union labelled goods and goods without any union label to pressing economic issues like runaway shops and imports. By the mid 1970's, Charles Garrahan, President of the Greater New York and Long Island ULSTC stated that "the import issue has become the major cause within our jurisdiction." Similarly, the recent union label slogan "Buy union - the job you save may be your own" captures the shift which has occurred in the union label movement from a focus on craft pride to one of economic survival.
Series XII is comprised primarily of materials related to annual conventions including minutes, correspondence, promotional materials and press clippings. Also of note are files and press related to the Coors Brewing Company boycotts. Additionally files and photographs related to the naming and dedication of Union Square are included in the collection.
Labor union-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor movement -- New York (State) -- New York; Service industries workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor union emblems -- New York (State) -- New York.; Union labels.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Union Square (New York, N.Y.); Boycotts.; Conference proceedings; Avrutin, Harry; Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island; American Federation of Labor. Union Label Trades Dept. (Philadelphia, Pa.); American Federation of Labor. Union Label Trades Dept. (Philadelphia, Pa.); Central Union Label Council of New York City; Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island; Coors Brewing Company; Union Label and Service Trades Department
- Series I: Union Label Advocate, 1918-1932
  - Union Label Advocate, 1918-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
- Series II: Union Label Store, 1916-1947
  Scope and Contents
  Includes minutes of Board of Directors (see microfilm), correspondence, audits, and financial reports.
  - Minutes, Board of Directors, 1916-1947 (Box 1, Folder 15-30)
  - Correspondences, 1925-1947 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Union Label Stores, Audits & Financial Reports, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series III: Central Union Label Council, 1911-1962
  Includes financial reports, 1940-1942; minutes of founding conference, 3/9/1911 and executive committee (see microfilm); and executive committee minutes, 1938-1962.
  - Central Union Label Council Financial Reports, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes of Founding Conference, 3/9/1911 Executive Committee, 1911-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1-27)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1938-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1-25)
- Series IV: Officers' Correspondence, 1919-1977; 1929-1977
  The Officers' Correspondence files document the work of the Union Label Council and Service Trades Department, in particular its efforts to publicize union labelled goods produced by organized shops (but only those produced by AFL craft unions until the 1955 merger). Because the New York City office functioned as a national information center, correspondents were rank and file unionists from around the country, as well as politicians (such as Mayor La Guardia and Governor F. D. Roosevelt) responding to the lobbying efforts of the Union Label Council. Other prominent correspondents are George Meany and William Green. Arranged chronologically with incoming and outgoing letters on the same subject filed together by the date of the last letter, the correspondence also highlights the key role played by the Secretary-Treasurer (Charles Sinnigen from 1919-March, 1949 and Harry Avrutin from Dec. 1949-1977). Major subject areas documented by the letters, reports, flyers, programs, telegrams, speeches, invitations and minutes are: investigation of "phoney" union labels, objection to registration of new union labels with the NYS Dept. of Labor (usually non-AFL labels), investigation of printed material without the Allied.
  Printing Trades Council's label, involvement with the planning for the NY World's Fair (1937-1939), the War Bond and Stamp Committee (1943-1945), strike and boycott information, planning for publicity events and arranging speaking engagements at union meetings and conventions. The sub-series reflect some of the community work of the officers - Sinnigen: Advisory Board on Vocational Education for the NYC Board of Education (a rich body of material on the development of vocational education), Non­ Partisan Committee of Queens County and the Board of Directors for the Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor. Sinnegen's reports and correspondence to the Union Label Trades Department, 1939- 1946, give full intelligence on CIO activities and AFL response in New York City. Avrutin: Trade Union Campaign of Brooklyn Women's Hospital, Board for Camp Minimum Wage and the National Labor Council of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, Inc. Affiliation applications are located in Series VIII.
  - Subseries A. General, 1919-1949
    - C. Sinnigen, Reports and Correspondence to the Union Label Trades Department, 1939-1946 (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
    - Sinnigen, Sec-Treas, 1919, 1929-1948 (Box 4, Folder 1-17)
    - C. Sinnigen, H. Avrutin, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Subseries B. Officer Activities, 1943-1947
    - C. Sinnigen, Advisory Board on Vocational Education, 1943-1947 (Box 4, Folder 19-24)
    - C. Sinnigen, Advisory Board of Vocational Education, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - C. Sinnigen, Medford Tuberculosis Sanitarium for Workingmen and Women and their families, 1927-1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - C. Sinnigen, National Committee on Prisons and Prison Label, 1941-1946 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - C. Sinnigen, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - C. Sinnigen, Subseries, Non-Partisan Committee of Queens County, 1937-1946 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - H. Avrutin, ULTD of NYS, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - H. Avrutin, CULC and ULTD of NYS, 1950-1955 (Box 5, Folder 10-19)
    - H. Avrutin, CULC and ULTD of NYS, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - H. Avrutin, CULC and ULSTD of NYS, 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 3-21)
    - H. Avrutin, CULC and ULSTD of NYS, 1967-1977 (Box 7, Folder 1-13)
- Series V: Union Label and Service Trades Department AFL and AFL-CIO, 1939-1977
  This series contains publicity material produced by the Washington office for labor press editors and for Union Label and Service Trades' Councils in the form of news releases, information packets, pamphlets, form letters and publications. The news packets primarily focused on suggestions for Union Label Week activities each year. The ULSTD used news releases to advise unionists about which goods to buy and which were to be boycotted (subjects - United Furniture Workers, Kingsport Press, UFW grape and lettuce boycott and the Farah boycott). In addition, the series includes the ULSTD's 1945 and 1946 editions of the Union Label Catalogue Directory and the 1964-1965 General Directory of Union-Made Products and Services. A small amount of publicity material for the Union Industries Shows staged between 1949 and 1972 is included. Files on the ULSTD's conventions are primarily made up of reports to the conventions by H. Avrutin in his capacity as Secretary of the Special Committee on State and City Union Label Councils and Women's Auxiliaries and as Secretary-Treasurer of the NYS-ULSTD.
  - ULSTD news releases publications, 1945-1976 (Box 7, Folder 14-16)
  - "Do not buy", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Union Industries Show, 1949-1972 (Box 7, Folder 18-21)
  - ULSTD's Conventions, 1950-1975 (Box 7, Folder 22-30)
- Series VI: NYS ULSTD Conventions, 1939-1977
  Series VI includes correspondence, resolutions, speeches, committee reports, and proceedings of Union Label conventions.
  - Union Label Conventions, 1939-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1-26)
  - Union Label Conventions, 1964-1977 (Box 9, Folder 1-16)
- Series VII: Financial Reports, 1938-1977
  This series is comprised of periodic audit reports prepared for the Union Label and Service Trades Council of New York and Long Island (1962-1969) and the ULSTD of NYS (1938-1977). Arranged by organization and by year, the reports present a statement of assets, liabilities and surplus and a statement of cash receipts and disbursements.
  - Financial Reports of ULTD of NYS, 1938-1961 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Financial Reports of ULTD of NYS, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Financial Reports of ULTD of NYS, 1969-1977 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Series VIII: Public Relations and Organizational Files, 1929-1976
  This series is comprised of correspondence, news releases, brochures and flyers developed by the Union Label Trades for publicity events to promote union made products. Highlights include files on the later years of the Labor Press Conference (1967-1970), the Label Trades weekly radio program on WNYC for discussion of labor issues. Detailed news releases for the radio programs during the years 1968-1970 provide information on topics and speakers.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Affiliates/Union label, 1964-66, 1972, 1974-76 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Affiliation Applications, Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Affiliation Applications, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Affiliation Applications - NYS Union Label, 1938-1939, 1942, 1950-53, 1959-60 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Brochures - Union Label, 1955, 1959, 1961, 1966, 1972, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Capital District (Albany) - Union Label, 1962, 1963, 1968, 1971-73 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Central Union Label Council Announcements, 1950, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Union Label Council Charter Applications, 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1951, 1961-62 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Labor Press Conference - Correspondents, 1967-1970 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Labor Press Conference - Radio Program (WNYC), 1960, 1963, 1967-70 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Mid-Year Meetings, 10/1/67, 2/20/74, 1/26/76 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - NYS AFL-CIO/NYS Union Label, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - NYS Union Label and Service Trades Department, "The Union Consumer" Newsletters, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - NYS Union Label/Districts (Oswego County, Rochester), 1943, 1960,1963, 1965, 1970, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Press Coverage, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Press Coverage, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Press Coverage, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Press Coverage, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Press Coverage, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Press Coverage, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Press Coverage, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Press Coverage, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Press Coverage, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Press Coverage, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Press Coverage, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Press Coverage, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Press Coverage, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Press Coverage, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Press Coverage, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Press Coverage, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Press Coverage, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Press Coverage, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Press Coverage, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Press Coverage, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Press Coverage, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Press Coverage, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Press Coverage, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Press Coverage, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Press Coverage, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Press Releases, NYS Union of Labor Service Trade Council (ULSTC), 1956, 1960-61 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Press Releases, NYS Union of Labor Service Trade Department (ULSTD), 1950-52, 1956-60, 1967-71 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Public Relations - Union Label, 1953, 1956-59, 1962, 1965, 1968, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Publicity - Greater NY & LI Union of Labor Service Trade Council, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Publicity - NYS ULSTD, 1955, 1959, 1960, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Speaking Engagements - NYS ULSTD, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Speeches By Union Label Officers, 1952, 1954-56, 1958, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Union Industries Information Center (UIIC) - ""Bulletin"" & Flyers, 1965-1976 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Union Label Council - New Jersey, 1/18/1946 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Union Label PR by Other Organizations, 1942, 1946, 1947, 1950, 1958, 1959, 1970, 1972, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Women's Auxiliary - Constitution & By-Laws, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Women's International Union Label League, Constitution, Ritual, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Women's Trade Union Seminar - Sponsored by Greater NY & LI ULSTC, at Hotel Commodore, NYC, 9/25/1974 (Box 10, Folder 53)
- Series IX: Union Label Activities, 1938-1976
  This series includes correspondence, leaflets, programs, and reports about events such as the Salute to Labor ballgame at Shea Stadium, the Union Label Pace at Roosevelt Raceway, Union Label Award of Merit Luncheons and promotionals such as the Little Miss Union Maid doll and the Union Industries Information Center set up for exhibits at the New York City office. Of special interest are the Miss Union Maid contest files which include application materials from women trade unionists (with a photograph and an essay about "what my union membership means to me") for five different contests during the period 1962-1972. Files on the Labor-Management exhibition trade show held annually between 1957-1979 comprise a majority of this series. It includes extensive correspondence with both unions and businesses in an effort to secure exhibitors of union-made products. These files document a very cooperative approach to labor-management relations.
  - Announcements from Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater NY and LI, 1952-1962 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Announcements from Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater NY and LI, 1963-1970 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Announcements from Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater NY and LI, 1971-1976 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Announcements from NYS Union Label and Service Trades, 1938-1964 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Announcements from NYS Union Label and Service Trades, 1965-1971 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Announcements from NYS Union Label and Service Trades, 1972-1978 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Announcements/Press Releases, Union Label of Greater NY and LI, 1954-1966 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Announcements/Press Releases, Union Label of Greater NY and LI, 1967-1976 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Announcements/Press Releases, Union Label of Greater NY and LI (miscellaneous), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Annual Buying Guide (Correspondences of), undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Labor Arts, 1968-69, 1972-74 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Labor/Arts News, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Billboard Campaign; Buyers' Guide to Union Made Products and Services of New York State, 16 "Annual" Directories Spanning the Years 1956-1976, 1958, 1956-1976 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Buyers' Supplement, Christmas, 1959, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dinner - Central Trade and Labor Council of Greater NY and Vicinity, 5/25/1938 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dinner - 35th Anniversary Dinner-Dance and Testimonial to Charles E. Sinnigen at Hotel St. George, 8/10/1946 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Dinner - 50th Anniversary Dinner of Greater NY & Long Island Union Label Service Trade Council at Hotel Commodore, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Dinner - Union Label Award of Merit Dinner to M. Mungovan, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Dinner - First Annual Greater NY Union Label Award of Merit to Reverend Philip A. Carey, 9/5/1962 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Dinner - Second Annual Greater NY Union Label Award of Merit to Robert F. Wagner, 9/4/1963 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Dinner - Fourth Annual Greater NY Union Label Award of Merit to Tomas W. "Teddy" Gleason and Jay Kramer, 9/8/1965 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Dinner - Fifth Annual Greater NY Union Label Award of Merit to Jacob S. Potofsky and Harold Rosner, 9/6/1966 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Dinner - First Annual LI Union Label Award of Merit to Irwin Fleischer and Myron Bienenfeld, 9/8/1966 (Box 11, Folder 19)